时间索引：03:50 - 设备，16:00 - 任务，
29:25 - 安全性与升级，36:00 - 计划开支，
46:30 - 怒斥，52:35 - 阿尔忒弥斯中好的部分，
55:45 - 总结
Hi, it's me, Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut,
嗨 我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
as you probably know, NASA is working really hard on getting humans back to the surface of the moon.
你可能知道 NASA正努力让人类回到月球表面
And if all goes well, we could see this happen as early as 2024.
如果一切顺利 最早可在2024年看到这一切发生
原作者名：Everyday Astronaut
视频来源：youtu.be/9O15vipueLs
原视频发布日期：20200913
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
And although I don't personally think that timeline is too likely to hold,
虽然我个人认为这条时间表不太可能保持得住
we haven't seen such an ambitious timeline for getting humans to the moon
我们还没有看到过如此艰巨的载人登月时间表
since the Apollo program, back in the 1960s.
自上世纪60年代的阿波罗计划以来
Not to mention the hardware exists.
更不用说设备的存在
Checks have been written and the astronauts are training to spend time on the moon.
支票已经开出 宇航员正在接受训练 以便在月球上度过一段时间
It's an exciting time to be alive,
活在这个时代令人兴奋
but unlike the Apollo program,
但与阿波罗计划不同的是
阿波罗计划1960-1972年总支出280亿美元(当时价格)大致相当于
美国1960-1972年总军费支出的8354.5亿美元(当时价格)的3%的天文数字
来源：www.planetary.org/space-policy/cost-of-apollo，
www.macrotrends.net/countries/USA/united-states/military-spending-defense-budget
which wound up putting 12 humans on the surface of the moon at an astronomical cost,
（阿波罗计划最终以天文数字的费用将12名人类送上了月球表面）
Artemis promises to be a sustainable program with an eventual lunar outpost
阿尔忒弥斯有望成为一个可持续发展的计划 并最终建立一个月球基地
and a permanent human presence at the Shackleton Crater on the South pole of the moon.
并在月球南极的沙克尔顿环形山 建立永久的人类存在
Yeah, that's right now we're talking. I mean, come on.
是啊 这才是有趣的地方 我是指 得了吧
This is the 21st century.
这是21世纪
You'd sure hope we can get back to the moon cheaper, using better technology
你肯定希望我们能用更好的技术 更便宜地回到月球
and do it in a safer way than we did in the 1960s. Right?
同时还比60年代的方法更安全 对不对？
Right? So today we're going to answer the question.
对不对？所以今天我们要回答这个问题
Why does NASA think Artemis will be a sustainable program
为什么NASA认为阿尔忒弥斯将是一个可持续发展的项目？
when the SLS rocket and Orion spacecraft is so dang expensive
(特别是)当SLS火箭和猎户座飞船如此昂贵时
and it's going to take at least two launches to get humans and their Lunar Landers to the moon.
而且至少需要两次发射 宇航员和登月舱才能到达月球
This can't be more sustainable than Apollo, right?
这不可能比(只要一发就能登月的)阿波罗更可持续 对吧？
b23.tv/av285667766
Well, we didn't even begin to scratch the surface of the costs in my last video about SLS versus Starship.
好吧 在我上一个关于SLS和Starship的视频中 甚至一点都没提到成本的细节
So today we're going to really dive into the total costs,
所以今天我们要深入探讨一下总成本
including development, infrastructure, and hardware,
包括开发 基础设施和设备
by giving SLS and Orion a full cost audit,
通过对SLS和猎户座飞船进行全面的成本审计
but we'll even show you how the Apollo and Artemis mission profiles differ,
但我们甚至还要告诉你 阿波罗和阿尔忒弥斯的任务概况有何不同
including the specific orbits and the rendezvous
包括具体的轨道和交会对接
and everything required to get humans to the surface of the moon.
以及载人登月所需的一切
And we'll even talk about the upgraded safety considerations and hardware involved.
我们甚至会讨论升级后的安全考虑和相关设备
Once we look at all of these details, we can answer the question.
一旦我们研究了所有这些细节 我们就可以回答这个问题了
Over 50 years later, is the Artemis program, actually an improvement over the Apollo program,
50多年后 阿尔忒弥斯计划实际上是改进了阿波罗计划
or is NASA going completely in the wrong direction when returning humans to the moon,
或者说 NASA在将人类送回月球时 完全走错了方向
let's get started.
让我们开始吧
-  [任务控制]三 二 一
- [Mission Control] Three, two, one,
起飞
and liftoff!
-  [尼尔]这是对人类的一小步
- [Neil] That's one small step for man.
-  [任务控制]这是休斯敦和一号测试的通信
- [Mission Control] That's Houston contact for the test one.
Welcome to part two of talking about SLS and comparing it to,
欢迎来到谈论SLS(视频系列)的第二部分 并对其进行各种比较
I guess, really everything at this point.
我觉得 这个各种比较 应该涵盖了目前已知的所有东西
b23.tv/av285667766
Part one, we really just focused on SLS versus Starship
第一部分里 我们真的只是专注于SLS与Starship的对决
and explaining kind of why the two programs exist at the same time.
并解释为什么这两个计划同时存在
Now you don't have to watch that video to make sense of this one,
现在为了看懂这个视频 你不需要看那个视频
but there is a lot of stuff that will help you understand the context
但有很多东西可以帮助你了解背景
and put things kind of in their place before you watch this one.
还能祛魅
So if you haven't seen that yet, definitely give that a watch,
所以 如果你还没有看过 一定要看一看
but we were just getting started in that video because here's the deal,
但是在那个视频里 话题才刚刚展开 因为
honestly, it's really, really, really hard,
老实说 这是 真的x3 很难
almost impossible to responsibly compare a government program with cost-plus contracting
几乎不可能负责任地将一个带有成本加成合同的政府项目
to a private companies, incredibly ambitious, and yet to be fully developed vehicle.
和一个超有野心 还没开发完的私人公司的项目进行对比
So instead in part two,
与之相反 在第二部分
we're going to focus more on comparing SLS and Orion to Apollo.
我们要把更多的精力放在比较SLS和猎户座与阿波罗上
不像Starship HLS版只是老马在登火航天器上砍几刀
Since of course the two programs have the same goal of getting humans on the moon,
当然是因为这两个计划目标一致 就是载人登月
but we're really going to dive into the weeds here
但我们真的要深入到细节中去了
and now because of that, this is a long video.
所以 这是一个很长的视频
So you'd better grab yourself a drink, get a notepad,
所以 你最好拿下自己的饮料还有笔记本
find a comfy chair and get ready for some learning.
找个舒服的椅子 准备好学习吧
But as always, here's the timestamps for these sections.
但和往常一样 这里是这些章节的时间戳
索引：03:50 - 设备，16:00 - 任务，
29:25 - 安全性与升级，36:00 - 计划开支，
46:30 - 怒斥，52:35 - 阿尔忒弥斯中好的部分，
55:45 - 总结
There's links in the description.
在描述中有(时间戳的)链接(b站不支持)
And the timeline here on YouTube is broken up by the sections as well.
YouTube上的时间轴也是按章节划分的(b站不支持x2)
And of course, there's an article version of this video,
当然 这个视频还有一个文章版本
which includes sources and methodology for easy searching and references.
其中包括来源与方法 方便搜索与参考
设备
I think a lot of people assume Artemis is just Apollo 2.0,
我想很多人都认为阿尔忒弥斯只是阿波罗2.0,
and we're basically just going to repeat what NASA did in the 60s and hopefully cheaper.
我们基本上是在重复60年代NASA的工作 希望能更便宜一些
Well, that's not really true at all.
其实根本不是这样的
This time NASA is doing things quite a bit differently
这一次NASA的做法有很大的不同
and that cheaper part, certainly up for debate.
而这便宜的部分 当然有待商榷
If we just look at the mission profiles here,
哪怕只看这里的任务概况
we can get a sense for just how different these two vehicles and programs really are,
我们就可以了解到这两种航天器和计划到底有多大的不同
but let's start off by putting up just the different vehicles like we did in our last video.
但是一开始 只是像上个视频一样 把不同的航天器放在一块比较
So again, sorry, some of this is going to be just a little bit of a repeat from the last video.
所以 再次抱歉 有些内容会是上一个视频的重复
There's three main vehicles for Apollo and Artemis.
阿波罗和阿尔忒弥斯都有三个主要的航天器
These are the launch vehicle, the Lunar Lander and the command module.
也就是运载火箭 登月舱和指令舱
Of course,
当然了
the launch vehicle is the rocket or rockets that gets everything into orbit and off to the moon.
运载火箭是将所有东西送入轨道并飞向月球的火箭
It's definitely one of the most exciting parts of each mission.
这绝对是每次任务中最激动人心的部分之一
考虑到大多数人买不起土豪用的超大望远镜
And certainly it's the only thing you can really witness with your own eyes in person.
当然 这也是唯一能让你亲眼目睹的事情
The Lunar Lander is pretty self explanatory.
登月舱 字面意思
It's the Lander that lands on the lunar surface hence, Lunar Lander.
就是降落在月球表面的着陆器
For each and every kilogram of mass you send to the surface of the moon,
你每向月球表面送去1kg的质量
it takes almost 200 kilograms of rocket to get it there.
它需要近200kg的火箭才能到达那里
So you want the Lunar Lander to be as lightweight as possible.
所以你希望登月舱尽可能的轻巧
And because Lunar Landers don't ever need to fly through Earth's atmosphere,
因为登月舱不需要通过地球大气层
they can be super stripped-down and even have landing legs that are so weak,
可以做得特别精简 甚至连着陆腿都是那么的脆弱
they wouldn't even hold the craft up on Earth
脆弱到在地球重力下连飞船自身都撑不起来
because they're designed to only be used on the moon with its lower gravity.
因为在设计上 着陆腿只能在重力较低的月球上使用
The command module is where the astronauts hang out during the majority of the mission,
指令舱是宇航员在大部分任务中的活动场所
but it's especially important during ascent and re-entry,
但在上升和再入时尤为重要
because sitting on top of what's essentially a giant bomb with a nozzle is quite dangerous,
因为本质上宇航员是坐在是一个带有喷嘴的巨大炸弹的顶部 是相当危险的
注意 - 这只是一个测试。没人在爆炸中受伤。
having a command module that can abort safely is generally considered a very good idea.
通常情况下指令舱最好可以安全地中止发射
Now, of course, I've already done way too many videos on abort systems,
那么 当然 我已经做了太多关于中止系统的视频
youtu.be/5IRdZjjq1Ik
including the one about the Gemini capsule's ejection seats,
包括关于双子座指令舱的弹射座椅的
b23.tv/av82858385
another one about why SpaceX and Boeing are now using liquid fueled systems
另一个关于为什么SpaceX和波音(在逃逸系统上)使用液体燃料系统的
b23.tv/av84145672
and even why Starship doesn't seem to have an abort system and whether or not it should.
甚至是关于为什么Starship好像没有中止系统以及是否应该有中止系统的
So if you want to know anything about abort systems,
所以如果你想了解任何关于中止系统的事情
I've definitely got you covered.
我肯定已经提到了
And unlike the Lunar Lander,
而且和登月舱不同的是
the command module needs to handle atmospheric flight,
指令舱需要应对大气层中的飞行
specifically the brutal reentry heat and landing portions of the mission.
特别是任务中残酷的再入热和着陆部分
For these two programs, the command module's utilize an ablative heat shield,
在这两个计划中 指令舱使用了一个烧蚀性隔热板
which intentionally flakes off material taking heat away with it.
烧蚀性隔热板是指故意让材料剥落并带走热量
Okay, so let's pull up both systems that will be taking humans to the moon,
好了 那让我们把两个登月系统都拉出来溜溜
starting with the command modules.
从指令舱开始
Although they might look similar, the Apollo capsule and the Orion capsule are quite different.
虽然它们看起来很相似 但阿波罗指令舱和猎户座指令舱有很大的不同
The Orion capsule is five meters wide versus the Apollo capsule's 3. 9 meters wide.
猎户座指令舱有5m宽 而阿波罗指令舱只有3.9m宽
It sports an impressive nine cubic meters of habitable volume compared to 6. 2 meters.
它的可居住容积为9m³ 而阿波罗指令舱只有6.2m³
So it's around 50% more volume,
所以 它的体积大约多了50%
and it's quite a bit more roomy obviously and capable of up to 6 astronauts,
而且它的空间明显大了不少 能够容纳6名宇航员
although it'll probably only fly four for the Artemis missions versus the Apollo's three,
虽然在阿尔忒弥斯任务中只会容纳4人 而阿波罗则为3人
which the Apollo capsule could technically fit five astronauts for rescue missions,
其中阿波罗指令舱在技术上可以容纳5名宇航员进行救援任务
but just barely.
但只是勉强
But what might be surprising is each vehicle's mass.
但可能让人惊讶的是每个航天器的质量
The Orion capsule and its service module are 26,520 kilograms fully fueled,
猎户座指令舱和它的服务舱完全加满燃料的质量是26.52t
which is surprisingly lighter than the Apollo capsule and its service module, which are 28,800 kilograms.
竟然比阿波罗指令舱及其服务舱轻了2.28t
But just looking at these two,
但只看这俩(外观)
you can tell they're basically backwards from each other.
你会发现它俩基本上是相反的
The Apollo command module was pretty small and had a large service module.
阿波罗指令舱是相当小的 但服务舱较大
And Orion is pretty much the opposite of that,
而猎户座差不多就是这种搭配的反面
a pretty large command module and a relatively small service module.
也就是一个相当大的指令舱和一个相对较小的服务舱
This means the Orion capsule and its service module have much less Delta-v
这意味着猎户座指令舱及其服务舱的速度增量(dv)值要少得多
or the ability to change its velocity than the Apollo capsule and service module.
或者说 比起阿波罗的指令舱和服务舱 其改变速度的能力差不少
In fact, the Orion capsule and the service module
事实上 猎户座的指令舱和服务舱
doesn't even have enough Delta-v to get into an out of low lunar orbit
甚至没有足够的dv(从地月转移轨道)往返月球低轨道
with only around 1,200 meters per second of Delta-v
其dv只有1200m/s左右
versus the Apollo capsule and its service module,
对比阿波罗指令舱和服务舱
which had over twice as much at around 2, 800 meters per second of Delta-v.
它的dv有猎户座的两倍多 达到了2800m/s
For those unfamiliar, Delta-v is how much a spacecraft can change its velocity in space.
对于那些不熟悉的人来说 dv是指航天器在太空中的速度变化幅度
It's a combination of the mass of the vehicle,
它考虑了航天器的质量
the mass of the payload and the mass of the propellant,
有效载荷的质量和推进剂的质量
mixed with the amount of fuel available to burn and the efficiency of the engines.
再加上可供点火的燃料质量和发动机的效率
So you can kind of think of it in the same way
所以 你可以用以下方式近似地看待它
as the range of a car which factors in the efficiency of the engine,
如同汽车的续航里程会考虑发动机效率
the size of the fuel tank and how much the car to push around.
油箱的大小和油门的大小
Now, if you're a little bit confused on why we're talking about Delta-v
现在 如果你仍然搞不清楚我们为什么要讨论dv的问题
and you still don't really get it, don't worry.
那么别担心
It will get less confusing, cause we're going to show you why this matters,
后面会讲到为什么这很重要
because this little fact right here makes a huge difference in
因为dv这件事
how each system gets astronauts to the moon
会很大地影响载人登月的过程
and why orbits of these two programs are extremely different.
或者说很大地影响登月的轨道
Okay. So speaking of extremely different,
好吧 所以说到极度不同
let's look at the Lunar Landers next.
接下来让我们看看登月舱
Now this is going to be fun to talk about because we actually get to talk about four different Lunar Landers.
这将是一个有趣的话题 因为我们实际上要讨论四个不同的登月舱
Since there's currently three Lunar Landers selected for development for the Artemis program.
因为目前有三台登月舱被选为阿尔忒弥斯计划的开发对象
For the Apollo program,
对于阿波罗计划
of course we have that iconic Apollo lunar module sometimes called the LEM or lunar excursion module.
当然 我们有那个标志性的阿波罗月球舱 有时也被称为LEM或月球游览舱
This spidery looking vehicle produced by Grumman
这个由格鲁曼公司生产的看起来像蜘蛛一样的航天器
stood seven meters tall, 9.4 meters wide with its legs extended
展开着陆腿的情况下 高7m 宽9.4m
上升级
2.445t干质量
16kN推力(约9.9t月球表面推力)
下降级
2.034t干质量
44kN推力(约27.2t月球表面推力)
RCS推进器
and weighed up to 16,400 kilograms, fully fueled.
加满燃料后重达16.4t
It could carry two astronauts to the surface of the moon for up to 75 hours.
它可以载着两名宇航员在月球表面停留75小时
For the Artemis program, we have the human landing system,
对于阿尔忒弥斯计划 我们有载人登月系统
which is a set of commercial contracts,
这是一套商业合同
more akin to the Commercial Crew Program than it is SLS and Orion.
比起SLS和猎户座 它更类似于商业载人计划
So basically NASA left out any strict guidelines
所以 NASA基本上没有设置任何严格的准则
and accepted bids that thought they could get a system to the moon within that ambitious 2024 timeline.
接受符合要求的投标 也就是他们认为 可在2024年这个艰巨的时间表内登月的那种
At the moment, we don't have a ton of details on all these systems yet.
目前 我们还没有这些系统的大量细节
So for now,
那么 就目前而言
we're just going to put up a rough size estimation of all these systems.
我们只要把这些系统的粗略估计的尺寸放在这
They're intended to have up to four astronauts for up to two weeks per mission.
他们的目的是让四名宇航员 在每次任务中最多停留两周
Currently there's three incredibly different vehicles.
目前有三种非常不同的航天器
Although NASA might down-select to two in 2021,
尽管NASA可能会在2021年减少到两艘飞船
the three currently chosen and into the next phase of development
但目前还是选定了三个项目 且能进入下一阶段的发展的
are the Blue Origin led National Team, Dynetics and SpaceX with a lunar version of their Starship.
也就是蓝色起源领导的国家队 Dynetics和SpaceX的月球版Starship
The National Team Lander features a Blue Origin Lander stage,
在国家队登月器中 蓝色起源负责开发下降级(着陆级)
a Lockheed Martin ascent stage, a Northrop Grumman transfer element vehicle
洛克希德马丁负责上升级 诺斯罗普格鲁曼负责转移级
and Draper developing the descent guidance and flight avionics.
以及德雷珀负责的下降制导和飞控设备
The system is about two thirds reusable with only the lunar lander portion being used once.
该系统大约有三分之二可以重复使用 只有下降级部分是一次性的
At first, although I speculate it could eventually be refueled on the surface
当然 一开始时下降级是一次性的 尽管我推测它最终可以在月球表面重新加注燃料
and if there's enough Delta-v they could maybe reuse the Lander as well.
如果有足够的dv 他们可能会重复使用着陆器
I don't really know.
我也不知道
The National Team Lander will likely fly on a few of Blue Origin's New Glenn rockets,
国家队着陆器很可能会用几枚蓝色起源的新格伦火箭进行发射
but it might fly on some other rockets,
但也可能用别的火箭发射
including segments being flown as co-manifest payloads on an upgraded SLS Block 1-B
比如将国家队着陆器部件中的几个 作为SLS的升级版Block 1-B的共同载荷进行发射
We don't really have those details yet though.
不过我们还没有真正掌握这些细节
The Dynetics Lander is a low slung, perhaps wiener-dog-esque lunar lander.
Dynetics登陆器是一个低矮的 腊肠狗式的登月舱
And it's a very unique looking thing here with over 20 subcontractors
它的外观非常独特 有20多个分包商参与其中
with the most notable being Draper, Sierra Nevada, United launch Alliance, And Thales Alenia.
最著名的有德雷珀 内华达山脉 联合发射联盟(ULA)和泰雷兹阿莱尼亚公司
It features eight landing engines that are fully reusable for multiple missions.
它带有8个可重复使用的着陆发动机 可以执行多次任务
With the only thing thrown away with each landing is a simple pair of fuel tanks.
每次着陆时唯一被扔掉的就是一对简单的燃料箱
The Lander can fit on a single SLS 1B cargo version,
着陆器可以装在一个SLS 1B货运版上
or they also mentioned it could be flown in segments on ULA's upcoming Vulcan rocket.
或者他们也提到还可以在ULA未来的火神火箭上分段发射
I am not really sure how many launches did take,
我不太清楚这到底要分几次发射
but I'm guessing it have to be like at least two Vulcans to get a Lander of that size to the moon.
但我觉得至少要两枚火神火箭 才能把这么大的着陆器运到月球上
Lastly, to the shock of pretty much everyone,
最后 令所有人震惊的是
NASA chose SpaceX's Starship as an option too.
NASA也选择了SpaceX的Starship
Now this version is a Lunar Lander only,
现在这个版本专用于登月
and it's missing the aerodynamic features and additional heat shielding,
也就缺少了空气动力学特性和额外的隔热板
but also includes bonus landing engines near the top.
但也增加了靠近顶部的着陆发动机
Now Starship's reuse confuses me quite a bit
那么Starship的重复使用让我颇为不解
because I mean, for sure it'd be an awesome just outpost.
因为我是指 它肯定很棒 哪怕只是作为基地使用
Just keep that thing there.
只要把那玩意儿放在那儿
You have like a thousand cubic meters of habitable volume. Yeah.
你就有一个上千立方米的可居住空间了 没错
Just land it once and never touch it again.
只要降落一次 然后再别动它
*这个渲染视频描述的不是月球优化版Starship
If you are to refly it and reuse it,
如果你要重新发射并重复使用它
it actually has to go all the way back to probably low Earth orbit or at least Earth's orbit
它实际上得要返回低地球轨道 或者地球轨道
and be refueled through multiple refueling flights of a Starship tanker, which is no small feat.
并通过燃料版Starship的多次发射进行燃料补加 这可不是什么小事
So this does mean in order to pull off each and every mission, including the very first one,
所以 这确实意味着为了完成每一次任务 包括第一次任务
it's going to have to be many full stack, Super Heavy Starship launches back to back.
它将不得不使用很多全功能的 包含超重助推器的Starship并连续进行发射
Now we'll get more into this in a second.
那么 不久后会细讲这个问题
And in an upcoming video, we'll also talk about this a ton,
在那个视频中 真的会讲很多关于Starship月球版的问题
because we're going to be going over all the different payload options
因为我们要讨论所有不同的有效载荷选项
for getting Starship stuff to the moon,
也就是Starship到月球的运载能力
including refueling Starship versus kick stages, we're going to dive in really, really deep.
包括Starship的燃料补加对比上面级的使用 我们会深入研究 非常非常深入
I promise.
我保证
After the next phase of selection and more detailed proposals scheduled for February, 2021,
在2021年2月进行下一阶段的选择和更详细的提案的程序之后
we can do an update truly comparing the three Landers in this human landing system.
可以做一个更新的视频 真正比较一下这个载人登月系统中的三个登月舱
So just keep in mind that for the Artemis program,
那么(对于以上这么多信息) 只要记住 对于阿尔忒弥斯计划
each of these Lunar Landers requires its own ride to the moon
每个登月舱都需要独立发射
and they can't be launched on the same rocket that the astronauts will be launched on,
换句话说就是不能和宇航员搭乘的火箭一起发射
like the Apollo program did with the Saturn V.
也就与阿波罗计划中的土星五号不同
Lastly, the rockets.
最后 火箭
As you know, from my last video,
如你所知 在我上一个视频中
the Artemis program will be utilizing the space launch system or the SLS rocket
阿尔忒弥斯计划将使用太空发射系统 简称SLS火箭
to carry the Orion capsule and its service module to the moon.
将猎户座指令舱及其服务舱送上月球
The Apollo program utilized the mighty Saturn V,
阿波罗计划使用了强大的土星五号
which could carry the Apollo command module and service module and the lunar module.
它可以携带阿波罗指令舱和服务舱 以及月球舱
Now as a refresher, here's the specs of these main rockets.
现在 也可以复习下 这里是这些主要火箭的规格
For the SLS, we're going to show you both the Block 1 and the Block 1B upgrade that may fly on later missions.
对于SLS 我们将向你展示Block 1 以及可能在以后的任务中发射的升级版Block 1B
Regardless, their lift off thrust is the same at 39.1 Mega Newtons,
这两种SLS的起飞推力都是一样的 为39.1MN(兆牛)(约3989.8t推力)
which is above the Saturn V's 35.1 Mega Newtons.
这高于土星五号的35.1MN(约3581.6t推力)
The LEO capacity for SLS is 95 tons or slightly more at 97 tons for the Block 1B
SLS的近地轨道(LEO)运载能力为95t 而Block 1B的LEO运载能力略高 为97t
请暂停观看：注意140t的LEO能力是把三级质量也计算上了，一般不这么计算有效载荷质量，否则按照此标准，SLS的LEO运载能力可达约180t。
译者个人认为土星五号的LEO能力按照去掉三级的土星五号改版(此型号无正式名称，火箭编号SA-513)实际发射的LEO载荷天空实验室的质量77t计算较为合适，
或者根据Saturn INT-21这一从未发射过的两级版土星五号的LEO能力87.88t计算也行，这样的计算方法符合当今各大国五型火箭的运载能力计算标准（确信）
注意INT-21并非SA-153，INT-21是将SA-153上本搭载在天空实验室上的火箭仪器舱移到了二级上。
天空实验室是土星五号三级改，所以土星五号的仪器舱在天空实验室上。
来源：en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saturn_V#Technology，www.spacelaunchreport.com/satstg5.html
and the Saturn V could put 140 tons into LEO.
而土星五号的LEO运载能力(*)为140t
The upgrade to the SLS 1B doesn't change the LEO capacity much
升级到SLS 1B后 LEO运载能力不会有太大变化
对于从航天飞机发展来的SLS，其飞行时序还是类似航天飞机，设计理念不同于煤油发动机作为一级的火箭
because core stage pretty much puts the upper stage into LEO
因为芯一级几乎是把上面级放到了LEO上
as we'll talk about more here in a second,
过一会我们会更进一步讨论
but by having a more capable stage in low Earth orbit,
但是芯级的LEO运载能力更强
it means the trans lunar injection capacity can increase.
也就意味着月球轨道进入能力可以增加(在上面级不拉垮的情况下)
And we call this the TLI capacity,
简称TLI能力
and it's just a measure of how much mass can the rocket send on a trajectory to the moon,
TLI是指火箭能把多少质量的载荷送到地月转移轨道
but not necessarily put in lunar orbit or land on the moon.
但不是送入绕月轨道 或者在月球着陆
It's just what it can shoot out towards the moon.
只是飞掠月球的能力
And notice the Block 1B four RL-10's on its much bigger Exploration Upper Stage
注意 Block 1B的上面级 探索上面级更大 有着4个RL-10
compared to the Block 1 of SLS,
而SLS Block 1的上面级就小一些
which only has a single RL-10 on the smaller Interim Cryogenic Propulsion Stage.
它的过渡型低温上面级上 只有一个RL-10
So that's why we see the difference here with the TLI performance of SLS at 27 tons or 43 tons with the Block 1B
那么 这就是为什么这里会标注两种TLI性能 Block 1的是27t Block 1B的是43t
请暂停观看：48.6t的TLI是阿波罗15号之后的土星五号的数据，是在原有土星五号的基础上进行了多种优化得到的，
如更靠南的发射角度，更低的停泊轨道，更少的燃料余量和一级上面的分级反推火箭，更多一级点火时间，同时二级减少纵向耦合震动，
来源：en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apollo_15#Launch_vehicle
至于阿波罗11号时期的土星五号，TLI只有41t(en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saturn_V#Technology)，
而SLS的TLI的停泊轨道显然高于升级版土五，这么比较不太公平
and the Saturn V was 48.6 tons.
而土星五号的TLI(*)是48.6t
Yes, it's really confusing that the less powerful Saturn V actually has more capability than SLS,
是的 性能较差的土星五号居然比SLS的能力更强 这真的很让人困惑
but having a three-stage rocket
但火箭是三级的
with two of those stages being huge high energy hydrogen stages definitely paid off.
其中两级还是能量(比冲)较高的氢氧火箭 指定有好果汁吃噢
And then of course in the Artemis program,
当然 在阿尔忒弥斯计划中
we'll see an array of other launch vehicles from Starship to Vulcan to New Glenn.
我们会看到一系列其他的运载火箭 从Starship到火神再到新格伦
And who knows, maybe even some new rockets or smaller rockets might end up playing a part in the program.
谁知道呢 甚至一些新火箭或者更小的火箭最终也会在这个计划中发挥作用
So these two programs have extremely different hardware choices and capabilities.
所以这两个计划的设备选择和运载能力都极为不同
So you'd probably think these hardware choices affect the missions.
那么你可能会认为这些设备选择会影响到任务
They sure do and boy are they different!
没错 是会影响到任务 但是老兄 它们不一样
任务
As you might know,
你可能知道
getting to the moon isn't as simple as
登上月球不是简单地
just pointing a rocket straight up blasting into space and slowing down when you get to the moon.
把火箭指向太空发射 到了月球再减速就可以了
Getting to the moon is not a straight shot.
到达月球不是直着去的
It requires some orbital mechanics and a few maneuvers to precisely get you there.
它需要一些轨道力学和一些机动动作来精确地把你送到那里
So we're going to show you the mission profiles here.
所以我们要在这里给大家看一下任务概况
And here's a little side note.
这里有一个小插曲
This is going to be kind of the eventual ish standard flight profile of
这将是一种最终的标准飞行概况
SLS getting into its near rectilinear halo orbit.
关于SLS发射进入近直线晕轮轨道(NRHO)的过程
But as of right now,
但截至目前
the first two or maybe three missions to the moon will either be flybys or slightly different orbits
前两次或三次登月任务要么是飞掠 或者是与NRHO略微不同的轨道
until the lunar gateway is parked there.
直到月球门户停在那里
But if the words is near rectilinear halo orbit sounds super confusing and intimidating,
但如果近直线晕轮轨道这名字 听起来毫无头绪还有点吓人
don't worry by the end of this section,
别担心 在本节结束前
you'll understand how it's different and why it's being chosen by NASA for the Artemis missions.
你会明白它的独特之处 以及为什么NASA会选择它来执行阿尔忒弥斯任务
So quick disclosure,
那么 快速说明一下
our timeline and our numbers are probably going to be a little bit off
接下来要讲的时间表和数据可能是有点偏差的
because Artemis doesn't even have these things published yet.
因为阿尔忒弥斯还没公布这些东西
And the first two or three missions will probably be quite a bit different than this,
而且前两三个任务可能会和这个有很大的不同
but this is just a generic
但这只是一个通用的情况
what eventually Artemis will likely be doing to get into that near rectilinear halo orbit,
阿尔忒弥斯最终可能要做的就是进入那个近直线晕轮轨道
but even our Apollo profile here is kind of generic
但即使是我们这里的阿波罗资料 也是一种通用的情况
since each and every mission had some unique variances.
因为每个任务都有一些独特的差异
So let's put both missions together and compare them side by side,
所以 我们把这两个任务放在一起 进行并列比较 (比较具有代表性)
别用谷歌卫星图看卡角，SpaceX陆地着陆场还停留在2017年以前的状态，只有一号着陆区，没有为重猎修建的二号着陆区，
译者推荐用必应卫星地图，谷歌辣鸡
which would theoretically be possible because SLS will take off from LC-39B
理论上是可能的 因为SLS将从LC-39B起飞
and the Saturn V took off almost exclusively from LC-39A.
而土星五号几乎完全从LC-39A起飞
Apollo 10 was the only Saturn V mission to launch from LC-39B.
(其中)阿波罗10号是唯一一个从LC-39B发射的土星五号任务
At lift off the Saturn V of course, ran on its five mighty F1 engines.
土星五号在起飞时(前) 当然使用的是五台强大的F1发动机
The SLS will fire up its four RS-25 main engines,
而SLS将启动四台RS-25主发动机
and then light it's massive solid rocket boosters when it's time to go.
然后在起飞时 点燃它那巨大的固体火箭助推器
And lift off!
接着起飞
The two rockets ascend pretty much vertically at first to punch through the atmosphere,
这两枚火箭一开始基本上是垂直上升 这样是为了冲破大气层
but they also pitch over down range to start accelerating horizontally
但也会朝发射方向向下偏转(程序转弯) 并开始水平加速
because after all to get to space, you can just go up out of the atmosphere,
因为毕竟要去太空 只需要竖着向上走
but to stay in space, you have to go sideways really, really fast.
但要想留在太空 必须要横着走 而且非常快
After two minutes and six seconds,
在发射后两分零六秒(T+02:06)时
the SLS's side boosters run out of fuel and are jettisoned.
SLS侧面的助推器燃料耗尽 被丢弃
At two minutes and 39 seconds,
在T+02:39
the Saturn V loses its first stage the S-IC and lights up its second stage the S-II.
土星五号分离了一级S-IC 与此同时其二级S-II点火
The SLS will run it's core stage and four RS-25's from sea level nearly to orbit,
SLS的芯级和4个RS-25将将从海平面一直运行到接近入轨
cutting off at eight minutes,
在T+08:00后停止运行
putting the upper stage and Orion into a highly elliptical suborbital trajectory
并将末级和猎户座送入高椭圆亚轨道
with an apogee of up to almost 2000 kilometers.
远地点可达近2000公里
They do this to discard the core stage,
他们这样做是为了丢弃芯级
so it can burn up on reentry
这样它就可以(可控地)在再入时烧毁
while still getting as much performance out of it as possible.
同时还能尽可能地获得更多的性能(而不需要降轨点火 也不需要长续航)
The Space Shuttle did something similar,
航天飞机也做过类似的事情
leaving the external fuel tank on a suborbital trajectory at separation.
在分离时将外部燃料储罐留在亚轨道上
The Saturn V S-II ran out of fuel just shy of orbit at eight minutes and 56 seconds into flight
在T+08:56 接近入轨时 土星五号S-II耗尽了燃料
and required the third stage, the S-IVB to fire for about two and a half more minutes
这就要求三级 即S-IVB再点火约两分半
until 11 minutes and 23 ish seconds to get itself into its parking orbit of 160 km by 160 km.
直到T+11:23 才进入160km x 160km的停泊轨道
The upper stage of SLS will do an orbit raise maneuver at its highest point or apogee.
SLS的上面级将在其最高点或(轨道)远地点进行轨道提升机动
And it'll bring up its perigee or lowest point from a suborbital trajectory to around 160 km or so
并将其近地点或最低点从亚轨道提升至160km左右
within the first hour of launch.
在发射后的第一个小时内
This is called the perigee raise maneuver or PRM.
这就是所谓的近地点提升机动或PRM
And it's what actually puts the Orion into orbit while allowing the core stage to reenter.
它实际上是在把猎户座送入轨道的同时 让芯级再入地球大气层
So now we've got our two spacecraft in wildly different orbits around Earth,
所以 现在这俩航天器(入轨后)环绕地球的轨道是非常不同的
preparing for their trans lunar injection or TLI.
并准备进行月球转移轨道进入(机动) 简称TLI
This is where they light up their engines and raise the orbit
他们在这里进行发动机点火并提高轨道高度
to basically intersect with where the moon will be.
提高后基本上是与月球(未来的)位置相交
Artemis missions after Artemis II
阿尔忒弥斯二号之后的阿尔忒弥斯任务
will do this on the first orbit,
将在绕行该轨道的第一圈时进行该机动
only about an hour and a half after launch,
这样 机动发生的时间就仅在发射后一个半小时时
but the burn will take a long time,
不过 点火的时间会很长
about 18 minutes long because of the low thrust that RL-10-B2 engine.
由于上面级RL-10-B2发动机的推力较小(约11.23t) 点火需要约18分钟
The Apollo missions did their TLI via a 350-second-burn
阿波罗任务则是通过350秒(约6分钟)的点火来完成TLI的
with its single J-2 engine on the S-IVB
使用的是S-IVB上的单台J-2发动机(推力约105.4t)
at 2 hours and 44 minutes after having orbited the Earth one and a half times.
点火发生在发射后2小时44分 绕地球一圈半之后
As those of you who have played Kerbal Space Program hopefully know
玩过坎巴拉太空计划(KSP)的朋友 希望你们知道
you actually raise your orbit ahead of where the moon is currently,
在你提升轨道时 实际上你(的相位角)要比月球靠前
specifically 67 degrees ahead for Earth.
特别是对地球(近地轨道)来说 是提前67度
And thanks to the orbital mechanics,
而由于轨道力学
your spacecraft will get to the moon at the same time as when the moon gets there.
你的航天器将在月球到达相交点的同时 到达月球
But just to make this animation and graphic look more simple,
但是为了让这个动画和图形看起来更简单
we're keeping the moon in a relative position to the Earth
我们让月球与地球的相对位置保持不变
KSP的天体自动对焦不香吗
because animating where it is continually throughout the mission gets very, very confusing.
因为在整个任务过程中 不断地改变它的位置会变得非常非常混乱
So just know if you raised your orbit where the moon currently is,
所以只要知道 如果你是和月球保持一样的相位角时提高轨道
you'd miss it by a lot.
你会错过很多
Within the first hour of the coast phase to the moon,
在到达月球的滑行轨道上的第一个小时内
the Apollo mission did something that's still pretty unique.
阿波罗任务会做一件很独特的事情
The command module with its large service module would detach from the S-IVB upper stage
带着大型服务舱的指令舱会从S-IVB末级上分离出来
and the S-IVB would open up a fairing that held the Lunar Lander.
然后S-IVB会打开一个里面有登月舱的整流罩(分离前处在服务舱下面)
Then the command module would turn around
然后指令舱会转过来
and dock with the Lunar Lander and extract it from the upper stage.
并与登月舱对接 将其从S-IVB中取出来
Once the two spacecraft were joined, they do some midcourse correction burns
一旦两个航天器连接起来 它们就会进行一些中途修正点火
to target about a hundred kilometers above the lunar surface on the far side of the moon.
点火后 近月点将修正为月球背面上方100km处
*地球和月球的大小以及之间的距离是按比例绘制，但是火箭的轨道并非实时
Now we're going to zoom out here and believe it or not,
现在我们要把这里放大 信不信由你
this is the actual scale of the Earth and the Moon,
这是地球和月球的实际比例
their size and distance is correct.
他们的尺寸和距离是正确的
Good thing we have high definition and 4K monitors and TVs,
好在我们有高清和4K的显示器和电视
because it's really hard to even see them together at this scale.
因为在这个比例下 真的很难同时看到它们
But since you don't often get to see these missions drawn out like this to scale,
但由于你不经常能看到这些任务按比例这样画出来
I thought it'd be really cool to actually draw it right,
我想如果真的能把它正确地画出来就太帅了
so you can get this perspective of how far away the moon really is from Earth.
这样你就能从这个角度了解到月球离地球到底有多远
It's pretty crazy. Isn't it? In fact, check this!
这是很疯狂 不是吗？事实上 看看这个
Watch how long it takes a beam of light or a radio transmission
看看一束光或无线电传输
地月单程延迟大约1.3秒
to get from Earth to the moon and back at this scale.
从地球到月球再返回需要多长时间
We can actually watch it go back and forth in real time.
我们实际上可以实时地看着它来回运动
Yes, this is real time.
是的 这是实时的
So that distance is what caused the transmission delays on the Apollo program.
所以这个距离是导致阿波罗计划传输延迟的原因
After a few days of coasting, next up will be the orbital insertion burn.
经过几天的滑行 接下来就是轨道进入点火
This is where the spacecraft slows down enough to be captured into lunar orbit.
这时 航天器会减速到足以被月球捕获进入月球轨道的程度
If the spacecraft's motor doesn't fire and it doesn't slow down,
如果航天器的发动机不点火 也不减速
the spacecraft could get slung out on orbit, putting it really far away from Earth.
就可能会被甩出(地球)轨道 并远离地球
That's terrifying.
那是很可怕的
So because of this,
正因为如此
Apollo missions usually aimed at a free return trajectory,
阿波罗任务(的月球转移轨道)通常使用自由返回轨道
meaning if nothing happened,
意思是如果什么都不发生
the moon's gravitational pull slings the spacecraft right back to Earth,
月球的引力可以将航天器直接抛回地球
but from Apollo 12 and on after a systems checkout post TLI,
但从阿波罗12号和TLI后的系统检查后
they would do a course correction and target their landing sites.
他们会进行航向修正 瞄准着陆点
But it wouldn't be a free return trajectory after that point.
但在那之后就不是自由返回轨道了
Because the Apollo missions generally aimed for a free return trajectory,
因为阿波罗任务一般都是以自由返回轨道为目标的
自由返回轨道详见en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free-return_trajectory
their initial apogee around Earth was higher beyond the moon,
所以它们最初的远地点都超过月球轨道
which despite being a longer total orbital period,
尽管这样的轨道周期较长
it does mean that they'll actually get to the moon quicker than Artemis will.
但是它们实际上仍会比阿尔忒弥斯更快到达月球
So although both vehicles will end up orbiting the moon,
因此 虽然两个航天器最终都会绕着月球运行
Artemis and Apollo orbit the moon in completely different ways.
但它们的方式完全不同
The Apollo program also did something that was not really ideal
阿波罗计划还做了一些并不理想的事情
because they would perform the spacecraft's lunar orbit insertion while on the far side of the moon.
因为宇航员将在月球的背面 进行航天器的月球轨道进入的机动
There was no communication during the entire 6-minute-burn that put the astronauts into lunar orbit.
在将宇航员送入月球轨道的整个6分钟的点火过程中 (和地面)没有任何通讯
For the Apollo program, this would usually occur a little after three days from launch.
对于阿波罗计划来说 这通常会在发射后三天后发生
The Apollo service module would first put the crew into a parking orbit
阿波罗服务舱会先将宇航员送入停泊轨道
of about 100 kilometers by 300 kilometers or so
约100km x 300km
before eventually circularizing and closer to a hundred km by a hundred km around the moon.
最终更接近月球并圆化成100km x 100km的轨道
And they were kind of equatorial ish in nature.
这些轨道都接近月球赤道
Instead of going around the far side of the moon,
不会像阿波罗计划那样 轨道总有绕到月球背面的时候
Artemis will aim just about 100 kilometers above the North pole of the moon.
阿尔忒弥斯将瞄准月球北极上方约100公里处
After about four to five days getting to the moon,
经过大约四到五天的时间到达月球(附近)
the Artemis missions will do their insertion burn,
此时阿尔忒弥斯任务将进行月球轨道进入点火
but they won't ever end up in a circular orbit.
但它们不会进入到绕月轨道
In fact, because of its small service module and low Delta-v,
事实上 由于服务舱小 dv少
the Orion capsule will barely get into lunar orbit at all.
猎户座指令舱几乎不能进入月球轨道
It'll eventually be a highly elliptical orbit of about 3, 000 km by around 70, 000 km
它最终将是一个高度椭圆的轨道 差不多是3000km x 70000 km
and only requires about 250 m/s of Delta-v to get into this orbit.
并且只需要大约250m/s的dv就能进入这个轨道
But this might vary mission to mission until there's eventually the Lunar Gateway parked in that orbit.
但这可能会因任务而异 直到月球门户停在这个轨道上
This particular orbit is that near rectilinear halo orbit that we've been talking about or NRHO.
这个特殊的轨道就是我们一直在谈论的近直线晕轮轨道 或者说NRHO
And it has a pretty big advantage for crew safety.
它对乘员的安全有很大的优势
Its unique orbit allows the spacecraft to be in constant contact with mission control back on Earth,
它独特的轨道能使航天器与地球上的任务控制中心保持不间断联系
because it never goes behind the moon from Earth's vantage point
因为从地球的有利位置看 它从来没有到过月球后面
[从地球上看的视角]
and NRHO's elliptical orbits go over the North and South poles of the moon,
而NRHO的椭圆轨道也会经过月球的南北两极
but the orbit is also perpendicular to the Earth,
且轨道垂直于地球
so the Earth can always see the spacecraft.
这样地球能始终看到航天器
The closest point of the orbit is at the North pole,
轨道的近月点在月球北极
which means the spacecraft spends the majority of its time South of the moon
这意味着航天器的大部分时间都在月球以南(远月点速度低)
with orbital periods lasting 6 to 8 days, versus the Apollo programs two ish hours.
轨道周期长达6到8天 而阿波罗计划的轨道周期大概2小时左右
Believe it or not a spacecraft or a space station can stay in this orbit
信不信由你 一个航天器或空间站可以在这个轨道上停留
with relatively little station keeping,
而且不需要太多轨道维持机动
since the Earth pulls at it equally the entire orbit.
因为地球(引力)在整个轨道上对它的拉动是一样的
It naturally wants to stay in the same orientation regardless of where the moon is relative to the Earth.
无论月球相对于地球的位置在哪 轨道(平面)都会自然地保持同一个方向
Unlike the Apollo missions,
不像阿波罗任务那样
which landed all over the moon ranging between 26 degrees North and 9 degrees South,
在月球26°N和9°S之间着陆
the Artemis missions will all land on the South pole of the moon at the Shackleton crater.
阿尔忒弥斯任务将全部降落在月球南极的沙克尔顿环形山
Once the vehicles were in their wildly different orbits, they'll hang out there for a bit of time.
一旦航天器进入了各自不同的轨道 它们就会在那里停留一段时间
In the case of the Apollo missions, they would usually spend around a day in lunar orbit
就阿波罗任务而言 它们通常会在月球轨道上停留一天左右的时间
before the crew of two would depart the command module
在此之后 两个乘员会离开指令舱
and fire up the Lunar Lander and begin their landing phase.
并启动登月舱 开始登月
Artemis' journey from here will be quite a bit different compared to Apollo.
与阿波罗相比 阿尔忒弥斯的旅程从这里开始将有很大不同
Once in lunar orbit,
一旦进入月球轨道
the Orion spacecraft will dock to either the upcoming Gateway
猎户座飞船将与即将到来的月球门户对接
that we keep kind of talking about, but not really, that's planned to be permanently in NRHO
我们一直在提到但从未详解 月球门户计划永久(服役期间)放置在NRHO
or until that's ready, it'll dock with the Lunar Lander, which will meet it in NRHO.
或者在月球门户部署之前 猎户座将与登月舱在NRHO对接
The crew of 2 to 4 that's to land on the moon will then transfer it to the human landing system
随后 登陆月球的两到四人小组将转移到载人登月系统上
and undock from either Gateway or Orion.
并从轨道门户或猎户座上分离
Once the human landing system is above the North pole of the moon,
一旦载人登月系统到达月球北极上空(近月点)
it'll lower its apoapsis, or apolune,
它会降低其远月点
and put the vehicle into a circular polar orbit around the moon.
并将航天器送入绕月的环形极地轨道
Now that we have both Landers in a more circular orbit and we're ready to land,
现在 这两台登月舱都进入了一个更圆的轨道 我们已经准备好降落了
the actual landing phase should be pretty similar.
实际着陆阶段应该是非常相似的
They basically slow down just enough so their trajectory intercepts their targeted landing site,
基本上就是减速到足够让轨道截住目标着陆点
and then they'll burn until they eventually touch down softly, right on target.
之后会进行点火 直到对准目标并软着陆
Okay. So as we mentioned before,
好的 正如我们之前提到的
the duration of hanging out on the moon can and will vary a lot.
每次任务在月球上停留的时间会有很大区别
From Apollo topping off at around 3 days to Artemis planning up to two weeks per mission,
从阿波罗的最多3天左右 到阿尔忒弥斯的2周
but now let's just fast forward and pretend it's time to get home.
但现在让我们快进 假装是时候回家了
Well from here, the two programs are pretty similar.
好吧 从这里看 这两个项目很相似
The Lunar Lander, or again, maybe just an ascent stage
登月舱 或者说 也许只是一个上升级
will take off from the lunar surface once it's lined up with the command module
一旦与指令舱对准 就会从月球表面起飞
so it can rendezvous with it.
以便它能与之会合
The Artemis missions will likely park in a low lunar orbit
阿尔忒弥斯任务很可能会停在一个低月球轨道上
before raising their orbits to match the Orion or gateway
之后会提高它们的轨道以交会猎户座或月球门户
and get into that Near Rectilinear Halo Orbit again.
并再次回到NRHO
The Apollo lunar module would only use the ascent stage to get into lunar orbit
阿波罗月球舱只使用上升级才能进入月球轨道
and would do so with a single burn that lasted just over seven minutes.
并将通过一次持续7分钟以上的点火来完成
It would then circularize its orbit at its apolune using just the reaction control system.
然后 它将仅使用反推力系统在其远月点圆化轨道
Otherwise known as the RCS thrusters.
反推力系统也就是所谓的RCS推进器
After, the Apollo Lunar Lander would dock with the Command Module and transfer over all of its moon goodies.
之后阿波罗登月舱将与指令舱对接 并将其所有的月球好东西转移过来
The lunar ascent module was jettisoned as the crew prepared for the trans Earth injection.
登月舱被抛弃 因为乘员们准备进行地球转移轨道进入
This again, would occur on the far side of the moon
这也将发生在月球的背面
away from radio communications during the entire two and a half minute burn.
在两分半的点火过程中 与地球无法进行无线电通讯
But back to Orion, it'll do something fairly similar
但回到猎户座 它会做一些相当类似的事情
after it's undocked from either the gateway or the human landing system
在它从月球门户或载人登月系统分离后
and prepare for its trans Earth injection.
并准备进行地球转移轨道进入
However, the ascent stage, instead of being jettisoned or discarded,
然而 登月舱的上升级 并没有被抛弃或丢弃
it's intended to be reused.
计划中是要对其进行重复使用的
And I think that's pretty awesome.
我认为这是相当不错的
Orion will do a 220 ish meters per second burn while flying over the North pole of the moon.
猎户座会(近月点)月球北极上空进行大概220m/s dv的点火
And again, because of that Near Rectilinear Halo Orbit,
同样 由于近直线晕轮轨道
it'll be within line of sight and communication with the Earth the entire time.
它会一直被地球看到并保持通信
So it'll take about the same amount of time to get back from the moon
所以每次任务中 从月球回来所需的时间
as it did to get to the moon for each mission.
和前往月球差不多一样
It took about three days for the Apollo missions to get back
从月球返回地球 阿波罗任务花了大约3天时间
and it'll take around five days to return home for Orion.
而猎户座则大约需要5天
Before reentry, each vehicle will discard their service module and flip facing heat shield first
再入前 每个航天器都会丢弃服务舱 并进行翻转 使隔热板朝前
youtu.be/ZZ-4xuVeBIE
then just like you might remember from that video I made about how you returned from orbit.
然后你可能还记得 就像我做的那个关于你如何从轨道上再入的视频
The Earth's atmosphere does the rest of the work.
地球的大气层完成了剩下的工作
Like I said, despite the destination being the same and the hardware looking quite similar,
就像我说的 尽管目的地是一样的 设备看起来也很相似
these two programs go about actually getting to the moon in incredibly different ways.
这两个计划的实际登月方式截然不同
So I guess this brings up the question is the Artemis program really any safer.
所以我想这就引出了一个问题 阿尔忒弥斯计划是否真的更安全？
安全性与升级
Why haven't we gone back to the moon since 1972?
为什么自1972年以来我们没有回到月球？
It's a very common question.
这是个很常见的问题
And there's a handful of reasons, way too many to go into right now,
原因有很多 现在无法一一列举
but perhaps the most common thought is
但也许最常见的想法是
why don't we just rebuild the Saturn V and the Apollo capsule do it all over again?
我们为什么不重建土星五号和阿波罗指令舱 并重新再这样做一遍呢？
Well, it doesn't take too long to realize
好了 比较容易得知
that the way we went to the moon with the Apollo program was incredibly risky.
使用阿波罗计划前往月球 有着令人难以置信的风险
And in hindsight NASA maybe dodged a bullet
事后看来 NASA也许躲过一劫
while driving a car on two wheels on the edge of a cliff inside of a tornado while buying lottery tickets.
就像在龙卷风的中心 一个悬崖边上开着只有两轮的汽车买彩票的那种
But oddly enough,
但奇怪的是
the hindsight risks weren't nearly as bad as the calculated risks of the Apollo program,
事后的风险并不像阿波罗计划计算的风险那样糟糕
which were wait for it
而这计算的风险是 你猜下(1秒钟)
5%,
只有5%的成功率
5% chance of surviving going to the moon and coming home safely.
5%的几率能活着登上月球并安全回家
Uh, yeah.
嗯 是的
Well, that's the numerical estimate for the probability of success beginning of the program,
嗯 这是在阿波罗计划刚开始时对成功概率的数字估计
not good, but this was a race to the moon.
并不好 但这是一场月球竞赛
And fortunately it went much better than a 5% chance of success,
而幸运的是 它比5%的成功率要好得多
but still a lot of things went wrong
但还是出了很多问题
and you don't have to be too familiar with the Apollo program to know
你不需要太熟悉阿波罗计划就能知道
how close almost every single mission came to full blown catastrophe at one point or another.
几乎每个任务都在某个时间点接近了全面的灾难
Here's a short list of just a few notable events.
这里只是列出了几个值得注意的事件
Of course, there's the Apollo 1 incident,
当然 还有阿波罗1号事件
which tragically led to the loss of three astronauts before the mission even started.
不幸的是 在任务开始之前 就有三名宇航员失去生命
It was just a training mission, uh,
这只是一个训练任务
but that led to the reconsideration of a pure oxygen environment,
但这导致了对纯氧环境的重新考虑
but also changed the pace for NASA and really kind of reiterated their safety considerations.
但也改变了NASA的速度 让他们对安全问题重新进行了考虑
Or of course,
或者说 当然
even famous Apollo 11 had a bunch of problems.
即使是著名的阿波罗11号也有一堆问题
b23.tv/av97474191
The computer set off multiple alarms, right before landing on the moon,
在登陆月球前 (登月舱飞控)计算机就触发了多个警报
which almost caused the entire system to fail,
这几乎导致整个系统的失败
not to mention the switch that activated the ascent stage to get off for the moon
更不用说为了离开地球的上升级的启动开关
got broken on return from the moonwalk.
从月球舱外行走后 返回时被(意外地)弄坏了
Buzz Aldrin had to use a felt pen to ensure the circuit breaker was in the correct position,
巴兹奥尔德林不得不用毡尖笔来归位断路器
ensuring they could fire up the ascent motor.
确保他们能启动上升级发动机
Apollo 12 was struck by lightning twice on ascent and it almost caused the abort of the mission.
阿波罗12号在上升过程中两次被闪电击中 差点导致任务的中止
Yes, this of course is where that famous SCE to AUX came from,
是的 这当然就是那个著名的SCE(信号调理电路)转AUX(辅助设置)的由来
which saved the mission.
(这个操作)拯救了这次任务
Apollo 13 was a mission that by all accounts should have been lost,
阿波罗13号是一次按理说应该失败的任务
but thanks to excellent communication, quick thinking,
但由于优秀的沟通 快速的思考
determination and the plucky nature of mission control and the crew,
决心和任务控制人员和航天器乘员的魄力
they managed to make it home safely.
他们成功地安全回家了
Apollo 15 only had two of its three parachutes open on reentry when returning
阿波罗15号在返回地球再入时 三个降落伞只打开了两个
resulting in a rougher than normal landing
导致比平时更加粗暴的着陆
and had one more failed, it would have likely led to the loss of crew.
如果还有一个降落伞没打开 很可能就有宇航员失去生命
And so on and so on and so on.
等等等等
NASA got really lucky that they took such big risks, but also reaped huge rewards.
NASA真的很幸运 他们冒了这么大的风险 但也收获了巨大的回报
Modern day NASA is much more aware of what failures do to a program,
现在 NASA更清楚失败对一个项目的影响
砍掉阿波罗计划的尼克松：我有姿势我自豪.jpg
especially one that doesn't have seemingly unlimited funding and support like the Apollo program did.
尤其是没有像阿波罗计划那样拥有看似无限的资金和支持的
The two Space Shuttle disasters
两次航天飞机灾难
were not only huge tragedies for the crew, the families and those involved in the missions,
不仅是乘员 家属和任务参与人员的巨大悲剧
but they were horrible politically and jeopardized NASA's funding and future programs.
但在政治上也是可怕的 并危及NASA的资金和未来计划
But as the Space Shuttle Program was being laid out,
但随着航天飞机计划的展开
NASA changed the way they certified and calculated risks.
NASA改变了他们认证和计算风险的方式
So nowadays NASA calculates the exact failure rate of each and every single component
所以现在 NASA会计算每一个组件的确切故障率
and evaluates the risk involved in each component, sub-component and system failing.
并评估每个组件 子组件和系统故障所涉及的风险
Okay. Okay. That's all great. Sure.
好的 当然 这很好
NASA now knows how to calculate risk better,
NASA现在知道如何更好地计算风险
and it'd be safe to assume
而且几乎可以肯定的是
that the Orion capsule, SLS and all other vehicles involved in Artemis
猎户座指令舱 SLS和阿尔忒弥斯所涉的所有其他航天器
will adhere to a much higher safety standard.
将坚持更高的安全标准
So here's a few fun, tangible upgrades in safety and performance to the Orion capsule
因此 在猎户座指令舱的安全和性能上 进行了一些有趣且切实的升级
compared to the Apollo capsule as a good example of some of those changes.
可以与阿波罗指令舱这个很好的例子进行对比
Orion has a massive upgrade and its aluminum pressure vessel with not only a new alloy,
猎户座进行了大规模的升级 其铝制压力容器不仅使用了新的合金
it's also friction stir welded for maximum strength and fewer defects.
还使用了摩擦搅拌焊的技术 以获得最大的强度和更少的缺陷
These upgrades allow the pressure vessel of Orion to be reused up to 10 times.
这些升级使得猎户座的加压舱体可以重复使用10次
The Apollo capsule ran on fuel cells,
阿波罗指令舱是靠燃料电池运行的
which famously all got knocked out during the Apollo 13 mission
很有名地 在阿波罗13号任务中全都被破坏了
and power consumption was one of the biggest factors in getting the crew home safely.
而且 电力消耗是影响乘员安全回家的最大因素之一
Orion will instead run on solar power and 120 volt lithium ion batteries.
而猎户座的电源会改用太阳能和120伏锂离子电池
Of course the interface and the computers have had a massive overhaul, as you can probably imagine.
当然 操作界面和计算机已经进行了大规模的改造 你大概可以想象
The interface is no longer heavy mechanical switches and hardware.
界面不再是沉重的机械开关和设备
It's instead sleek, lightweight,
而是时尚轻巧
and highly configurable computers with minimal mechanical switches only about 60.
还有高配置的计算机  最少的情况下 机械开关只有60个
And yeah, of course the computers on Orion are substantially upgraded from the computers from 50 years ago.
是的 当然 猎户座上的电脑比50年前的电脑有了大幅度的升级
Orion's computer is over a thousand times more powerful and there's redundant computers compared to Apollo.
相比阿波罗 猎户座的计算机强大了一千多倍 而且还装有冗余的计算机
Orion can communicate with the TDRS satellites
猎户座可以与TDRS卫星通信
or the tracking and data relay satellite system using phased array antennas.
TDRS全称跟踪与数据中继卫星系统 装有相控阵天线
And it can communicate with ground sites as well.
而且它还可以与地面站点进行通信
Navigation is massively upgraded
导航功能也得到了大规模提升
because Orion can utilize modern day GPS satellites when close to Earth
因为猎户座在接近地球时可以使用现代的GPS卫星进行导航
and when far away from Earth,
而当远离地球时
it has automatic star tracking equipment that's much more advanced than those on the ISS even.
它的自动星敏感器甚至比国际空间站上的设备要先进得多
Even the docking system has a new TriDAR or 3D laser range and a highly upgraded camera as well,
就连对接系统也有新的TriDAR 其带有3D激光距离雷达 除此之外还有高度升级的相机
which will enable auto docking.
这将实现自动对接
The thermal protection system features similar silica tiles to the Space Shuttle on the sidewalls of the spacecraft.
在航天器的侧壁上 热保护系统则带有安装了类似航天飞机的硅制防热瓦
And it has the largest ablative heat shield ever built
而且它拥有有史以来最大的烧蚀式隔热板
at five meters across and weighing a whopping 450 kilograms.
宽大5m 重达450kg
The seats in the Orion capsule,
猎户座指令舱的座椅
although they frankly look like a downgrade tinker toy version of the Apollo seats,
虽然它们看起来就像一个降级版的阿波罗座椅的玩具版
they're much lighter and can actually absorb more impact on landing.
但是更轻 而且实际上可以吸收更多着陆的冲击力
The parachutes are upgraded, of course,
当然 降落伞也是经过升级的
but even the way they're deployed are now run off redundant sensors.
但现在连降落伞的展开方式都用到了冗余的传感器
Apollo relied on barometric sensors only to determine chute activations.
而阿波罗只依靠气压传感器来确定降落伞的启动
Orion will have GPS and inertial measurement units as well.
猎户座将有GPS和惯性测量装置
Orion will even have better radiation shielding with materials, better suited to absorbing and deflecting radiation,
猎户座甚至会有更好的辐射屏蔽材料 更适合吸收和偏转辐射
but there's also considerations to make a temporary shelter in case of severe radiation storms.
但也有考虑制作一个临时的庇护所来预防严重的辐射风暴
Okay. Okay.
好的好的
So NASA has a lot of new safety considerations
所以 NASA有很多新的安全考虑因素
and has made the upgrades you'd expect to Orion to make it much safer than Apollo,
并且如你所愿 对猎户座进行了比阿波罗更安全的升级
but how much does all this increased safety cost us?
但所有这些增加的安全成本是多少呢？
What happened to this new sustainable program?
这个新的可持续 发展计划发生了啥？
Well, the cost rabbit hole was about to begin...
嗯 无底洞一样的开支话题即将开始
计划开支
Let's actually peel these onion layers back here
让我们实际剥开这些洋葱层
and get really, really deep into this because why not?
并且进行深入的研究 为什么不呢
And in our last video we made some pretty blanket assumptions.
而在上一个视频中 我们做了一些很空泛的假设
So we should probably dig deeper into this because talking about price is insanely hard
所以 我们也许应该更深入地研究这个问题 因为谈论价格是非常困难的
when programs include development, operations, and hardware.
当这些计划包括开发 运营和设备的时候
Now here's the deal we had to of course take some assumptions in order to calculate some of this stuff.
现在因为 我们当然得做一些假设来计算其中的一些东西
So to project into the future to get a sense of how much some of this stuff costs.
这样才好预测到未来 才能知道这些东西的成本是多少
That being said here is a real rough and conservative estimate of
这里真的是一个粗略和保守的估计
how much Artemis will cost from Artemis I through Artemis 8.
关于阿尔忒弥斯从一号到八号的成本是多少
To date, the SLS program has cost about $16 billion.
到目前为止 SLS计划已经花费了大约160亿美元
And Orion has cost about $12.5 billion if you count from only 2011 on.
而猎户座的成本约为125亿美元 如果你只从2011年开始计算的话
So not including the five years of development during the Constellation program.
所以还不包括星座计划的5年开发时间
Now based on the Office of Inspector General's report in 2020 on the cost and future costs of
现在根据监察长办公室(NASA OIG)在2020年做的成本和未来成本的报告
SLS, Orion, the mobile launch tower and infrastructure,
这之中包括SLS 猎户座 移动发射塔和基础设施
we can project what will take to get us to Artemis 1, the first uncrewed flight around the moon.
我们可以推算出需要什么才能让我们到达阿尔忒弥斯1 第一次无人绕月飞行任务
By Artemis 1, the SLS program will have spent about $18. 3 billion
到了阿尔忒弥斯1 SLS计划将花费约183亿美元
and the Orion program will have gone through about 13.6 billion.
而猎户座则是136亿
But now some of that budget has already gone into purchasing a future missions and hardware.
但现在 其中一部分预算已经用于购买未来的任务和设备了
The first flight with humans is Artemis II, which again,
首次载人飞行的是阿尔忒弥斯2 同样
features an SLS and an Orion capsule going out around the moon on a free return trajectory.
是一个SLS和一个猎户座飞船以自由返回的轨道进行绕月飞行
And again, based on the OIG report, if that happens in 2023,
再根据OIG的报告 如果这在2023年发生
NASA will have spent about 38.4 billion on the program in total.
NASA将在该计划上总共花费约384亿
That doesn't sound good, does it?
这听起来不妙啊
But hold on here comes some good ish news.
不过 等一下这里就有一些好消息了
Now, at this point, the program will have a more stable production line
那么 到这之后 阿尔忒弥斯就会有一个比较稳定的生产线
and NASA has already agreed to purchase SLS boosters at $870 million
而NASA已经同意以8.7亿美元的单价购买SLS火箭
and 3 more Orion capsules at $900 million.
还有以9亿美元的单价购买至少3个猎户座飞船
After that Orion will come down to $750 million.
在此之后猎户座 会降到7.5亿美元一艘
Now being conservative with these numbers and annual budgets.
现在 对于这些数字和年度预算 得保守看待
If NASA only spends about $300 million a year to run an operate SLS
如果NASA每年只花大约3亿美元来运作SLS
and about $200 million to run an operate the Orion program,
还有约2亿美元来运作猎户座
we can project all the way out to Artemis 8.
我们可以一直推算到阿尔忒弥斯8号
Assuming we get one mission per year after Artemis II
假设我们在阿尔忒弥斯2之后每年都有一个任务
for a total of about 51.6 billion or about 6.5 billion per mission.
共计约516亿美元 即每次任务约65亿美元
But of course there's one very important thing missing from numbers so far
当然 到目前为止的数字中还少了一件非常重要的东西
that will make landing on the moon possible.
也就是用来登月的那个东西
That's the Lunar Lander,
登月舱
Oh right. That might be necessary.
哦 对了 这可得是必要的
NASA has already budgeted $4 billion
NASA已经计划了40亿美元
for the first year of the human landing system portion of the Artemis program.
作为阿尔忒弥斯载人登月系统部分的第一年的预算
Now a conservative estimate of the amount of money it'll take to finish the project,
现在保守估计完成这个项目所需的资金数额
get the first Lander built
建成第一台登月舱
and single rocket or multiple rockets to carry the Lander system out for Artemis three would be $10 billion.
以及使用单枚火箭或多枚火箭 为阿尔忒弥斯3运载登月舱系统的费用是100亿美元
And again, that's a very conservative estimate.
同样 这也是一个非常保守的估计
So now let's add the Lunar Lander, the launch and the annual program costs,
所以现在让我们把登月舱 发射和每年的计划费用加在一起
which would be about $3 billion a year.
这将是每年约30亿美元
And once the human landing systems are up and running and in a reusable state,
而一旦载人登月系统启动运行并处于可重复使用状态
we can lower the cost of operations to only 500 million,
我们可以把运营成本降低到只有5亿
which would help factor in general program costs and refueling launches and all those other considerations.
这包括了一般的计划成本 用于燃料加注的发射 以及其他因素
However, again, this is a very rough and conservative estimate.
然而 这又是一个非常粗略和保守的估计
Luckily, these services will be fixed price contracts.
幸运的是 (登月的)这些服务将是固定价格的合同(而非成本加成合同)
So once we know the actual costs, it will be virtually impossible to have costs overruns.
因此 一旦我们知道实际成本 几乎不可能出现成本超支的情况
So now running the math on the cost of the program divided by the mission.
所以现在计算一下计划的成本除以任务的费用
Artemis 1 would cost about $32 billion and Artemis II would come down to about $19.2 billion,
阿尔忒弥斯1将耗资约320亿美元 阿尔忒弥斯2将降至约192亿美元
but Artemis III would bring the cost to around $16. 9 billion because of that Lunar Lander.
但由于登月舱的存在 阿尔忒弥斯3的成本将达到169亿美元左右
If Artemis gets down to Artemis 8, they could get down below $9 billion,
如果阿尔忒弥斯持续到阿尔忒弥斯8 平均单次任务成本就可以降到90亿美元以下
average cost for each mission when you factor in the development costs.
当然这里是加上了开发的成本
Luckily because a lot of these systems and the landers would be reused and repurposed,
幸运的是 因为这之中不少系统和登月舱都会被重复使用
the cost could actually go down quite a bit from there,
(随着运营的持续) 成本实际上可以从最初那里下降不少
especially when you're depreciating all of the development costs from there and out,
特别是当你把所有的开发成本除去的时候
but reusing the hardware could really bring that cost down to something a lot more reasonable.
不过重复使用设备确实可以将成本降到更合理的程度
But of course this all still sounds pretty expensive,
不过当然这一切听起来还是挺贵的
but we don't really have anything to compare it to yet.
但我们还没有任何东西可以与之相比
So how do the costs compare to the Apollo program?
那么与阿波罗计划相比 成本如何呢？
The Apollo program costs about $28 billion between 1961 and 1973,
阿波罗计划在1961年到1973年之间花费了大约280亿美元
according to a very thorough report by the Planetary Society.
根据行星协会的一份非常详尽的报告
In today's money, that's about $283 billion.
以今天的货币计算 大约是2830亿美元
But this insane cost wasn't just for the missions to the moon.
但这个疯狂的成本并不只是用于月球任务
This includes all Gemini launches, lunar probes,
这还包括所有的双子座 月球探测器
all Apollo development and launches, all Saturn 1's,
所有阿波罗的研制和发射 所有土星1号
Saturn 1B's and Saturn V development and launches up until 1973.
土星1B和土星五号的研制和发射 并且一直持续到1973年
But that also includes the entire modern infrastructure that is the Kennedy Space Center,
但这也包括了肯尼迪航天中心的整个现代化基础设施
including of course the Vehicle Assembly Building, the launch pads,
当然包括航天器组装大楼 发射台
the crawlers, the Press Site, and dozens of huge office buildings.
移动发射平台 记者站 和几十栋巨大的办公楼
Plus basically everything at the Johnson Space Center in Houston, Texas,
再加上整个德克萨斯州休斯敦的约翰逊航天中心
the ground tracking stations,
地面测控站
the Stennis Cpace Center for testing the rocket engines,
用于测试火箭发动机的斯坦尼斯太空中心
almost everything out at Marshall Space Center and so on and so on and so on.
整个马歇尔航天中心 等等 等等
Okay.
好吧
So basically everything NASA was built during the Apollo era with some of that $283 billion.
所以基本上整个NASA都是在阿波罗时代建造的 其中有一些是用到了这2830亿美元
The Apollo program got us a lot more than footprints on the moon.
阿波罗计划给我们带来的不仅仅是月球上的脚印
But if we break that down to just the actual physical cost of the Saturn V,
但如果我们把它分解成土星五号的实际成本
the Apollo command and service modules and the Lunar Landers development and building budget seen here,
阿波罗指挥和服务舱以及登月舱的研制预算
that total comes out to be over half that at around 155 billion in today's dollars.
总额超过了之前那个数值的一半 以今天的美元计算约为1550亿
Okay. So now we're about to do something incredibly stupid
好了 现在我们要做一些难以置信的蠢事
and try and compare apples to light bulbs or something here.
就好比是让苹果和灯泡进行对比
And just be forewarned, there's almost no way to fairly compare these two,
而且事先提示一下 几乎没有办法公平地比较这两者
but nevertheless reminder, all costs are shown adjusted for today's dollar.
但不管怎样(还是比比看) 再说一下 所有的成本都是按今天的美元调整过的
If you take the $38. 3 billion spent to develop and build the Apollo command and service module
如果把研制阿波罗指令舱和服务舱所花费的383亿美元计算在内
and its share of costs from the guidance, navigation and instrumentation
包括其制导 导航和仪器设备部分的费用
and divide it by the 34 articles that were built, tested and flown,
并除以制造出来用于测试和飞行的数量 34
and you get a real rough per unit estimate of $1.4 billion in today's dollars.
这样粗略地估算下来 每艘飞船需要14亿美元
Then if we take the lunar modules $23 billion for development building
如果我们把登月舱研制所用的230亿美元
and its share of guidance, navigation and instrumentation
包括其制导 导航和仪器设备部分的费用
divided by the 25 articles that were built, tested and flown,
并除以制造出来用于测试和飞行的数量 25
and we end up with about $1.3 billion in today's dollars.
最后算下来 每个登月舱要差不多13亿美元
And lastly, the Saturn V,
最后是土星五号
if we take the total development cost of $66.1 billion plus its share of engine development
如果以661亿美元的总开发成本加上其分担的发动机开发成本计算在内
and divide it by the 17 that were built, tested and flown,
并除以制造出来用于测试和飞行的数量 17
we get about $4.5 billion per Saturn V.
于是 每枚土星五号就需要差不多45亿美元
Now, if we assume we'll get to Artemis 8,
现在 如果我们假设阿尔忒弥斯8会实现
we can take the program costs of Orion at $21.8 billion,
我们可以把猎户座的计划成本定为218亿美元
then divide it by the 20 or so units that will have been built tested, and some flown.
并除以制造出来用于测试和飞行的数量 大概20
We get a total price of $1.1 billion per unit.
得到每艘飞船总价11亿美元
Then the wildcard here, the human landing system.
接着是这里最难猜测的部分 载人登月系统
If we take what will likely be at least $17. 5 billion by Artemis 8
如果我们把至少175亿美元除以阿尔忒弥斯8次任务
and figure a total of let's say 12 units that will have been built tested, and some flown,
并除以制造出来用于测试和飞行的数量 假设有12个
we get a total of $1.5 billion per Lander.
得到每个登月舱15亿美元的价格
But again, this also does account for the rockets that will get them to the moon too.
但同样 这也要考虑到将它们送上月球的火箭(而阿波罗登月舱是一块送的 不需要考虑)
And notice that I did factor in 12 units,
请注意 我确实考虑到了12个(多于任务需要的6个)
even though we don't need one, especially for the first two missions of Artemis.
尽管某些任务是不需要登月舱的 比如阿尔忒弥斯的前两个任务
There might be multiple Landers involved by this point
(但这是因为) 前两个任务期间可能会涉及到多个登月舱
because some of them are going to do some un-crewed flight tests.
因为一些登月舱要进行一些无人飞行试验
Some of them might be sitting on the surface doing other things,
有些甚至要参与一些非载人的登月任务
but that might be almost all they ever end up building
但(一开始为测试制造的登月舱数量)也可能接近他们最终制造的数量
because don't forget these are going to be at least partially or even maybe fully reusable.
因为别忘了这些东西至少会有一部分甚至完全重复使用
So it would actually get cheaper and cheaper by a lot the more times they're used.
所以实际上会随着使用次数增加而更便宜(所以估算每艘的造价其实不太准确)
And now lastly, SLS.
最后提下 SLS
Let's take the $29.8 billion and then divide that by the 10 articles that will have been built.
让我们把298亿美元除以已经建造的10枚火箭
Some just tested and some are flown.
有的刚刚测试 有的已经飞行
And we end up with a total cost of about $3 billion per rocket.
我们最终得出的总成本是每枚火箭30亿美元左右
That's interesting.
这很有意思
Now there were substantially more flights and physical hardware units built, tested and flown during the Apollo era
那么 大体上 在阿波罗时代 参与测试与飞行的设备制造数量更多
than there are today for the Artemis missions.
而且单价还比今天的阿尔忒弥斯任务更贵
But then again, everything was more expensive back then.
但话又说回来 那时候所有的东西都很贵(即使除去货币贬值的因素)
I mean, they had to pretty much invent everything from scratch.
我是指 他们几乎要从头开始发明一切
You'd really hope we can make a cheaper spacecraft and rockets today than we could over 50 years ago.
你应该真的会这么想 我们今天是能制造出比50多年前更便宜的航天器和火箭的
And again, it might be easy to say, well, look at how much more we got out of the Apollo program.
而且再说下 说起来也很容易  好吧 看看我们从阿波罗计划中收获了多少
Considering we started from scratch.
考虑到那时是从头开始
It's going to take us roughly the same amount of money and time to do it again in the 21st century?
而在21世纪(用当年的概念)再做一次 我们要花的钱和时间(可能也会)大致相同吗？
Artemis isn't Apollo 2.0,
(因此) 阿尔忒弥斯不是阿波罗2.0
despite it being Apollo's sister in Greek mythology,
尽管它在希腊神话中是阿波罗的姐姐
Artemis is substantially safer, roomier and designed to spend a lot more time on the surface of the moon.
阿尔忒弥斯实质上更安全 更宽敞 而且设计上是为了在月球表面停留更多时间的
Now we didn't really even get into this
那么 我们甚至没有真正进入这个问题
since mission planning is still very much up in the air with the Artemis program,
因为阿尔忒弥斯计划的任务规划还在很大程度上还悬而未决
but even the shortest missions for Artemis will be nearly a week long
但即使是最短的阿尔忒弥斯任务 也会有近一周的时间
or over twice as long as Apollo 17, the longest lunar mission to date.
或者说是迄今为止最长的月球任务 阿波罗17号的两倍多
And Artemis can potentially take up to four astronauts to the moon at a time for up to two weeks per mission.
而阿尔忒弥斯有可能一次带着4名宇航员登上月球 每次任务时间长达2周
It could end up being over 10 times cheaper dollar per hour for each human hour on the surface of the moon
最终可能让每人停留在月球表面的单位小时价格便宜90%以上
compared to the Apollo program.
与阿波罗计划相比
Okay, so maybe what Artemis lacks an actual cost savings and timely schedules
好吧 也许阿尔忒弥斯缺少的是实际的成本节约和按时的计划
it makes up for in just sheer raw time and capabilities on the moon.
但大大增强了停留在月球上的时间和能力
So maybe we should look at some of the things
所以 也许我们应该看看
that slowed down and made SLS and Orion so over budget in the past
导致SLS和猎户座在过去如此超支
and see if we're doomed to see more of this stuff going forward in the future.
以及在未来 是否注定产生更多的超支
怒斥
And now, the moment you've probably all been waiting for a rant.
而现在 就是你们可能一直在等待的怒斥时间
I think one of the biggest frustrations I have with the Artemis program
我认为我对阿尔忒弥斯计划最大的失望之一就是
besides SLS's ridiculous costs and the fact that it is barely even capable of getting Orion to the moon,
除了SLS的可笑的成本 以及 它的运力只能勉强发送猎户座到月球
it's the fact that it's using hardware that's not only been mostly developed,
事实上 不仅使用的设备大多是已经开发出来的
but it's even pulling from an existing inventory of hardware to use as the basis of the vehicle.
而且甚至从现有的设备库存中拿出来用作航天器的基础
Now it's not the fact that they're reusing old hardware.
那么 事实上这并不是说他们在重复使用旧设备
I mean, in theory, that makes sense.
我是指 在理论上 可以这么解释
And of course you'd really only do this to save money, right?
当然 你这样做只是为了省钱 对吧？
So I guess that's where there's just such a big disconnect for me
所以我想这就是我的一大分歧所在
between the reuse of parts, contracts and infrastructure and the cost
这是指在部件 合同和基础设施的重复使用与成本之间的关系
because boy are there some costs.
因为兄啊 重复使用是要花钱的
The solid rocket boosters, which literally have all of the hardware necessary to make a whopping 16 boosters
固体火箭助推器 其拥有制造16个助推器所需的所有设备
has cost $2.4 billion.
已经花费24亿美元
$2.4 billion to take some empty shells of existing boosters
24亿美元 (不过是)将现有助推器的一些空壳
and refurbish and upgrade them to be five segment boosters.
并将其翻新升级为五段式助推器
Yes, of course they had to change out to a new propellant.
是的 当然 他们得换成新的推进剂
www.nasaspaceflight.com/2018/10/ngis-readies-srbs-first-sls-flights/
Yes, they had to upgrade some avionics and a plug,
是的 他们得升级一些航电设备 还有那个喷管喉塞
but for $2.4 billion,
但花了24亿美元
you would've thought that they had started from scratch and built an entirely brand new type of rocket booster.
你会以为他们从头开始制造了一个全新的火箭助推器
And oddly enough, Northrup Grumman claims when they get to the replacement booster, the BOLE booster,
而奇怪的是 诺斯鲁普格鲁曼声称 他们使用了新助推器 BOLE助推器替代SRB的时候
which is basically their core state of the Omega rocket [rest in peace],
(BOLE助推器基本就是他们OmegA火箭的芯级 安息吧OmegA)
they'll be able to produce those brand new boosters cheaper than the original reused ones.
此时生产这些全新的助推器 会比原来重复使用的助推器更便宜
迷惑.jpg
Or look at the RS-25's.
或者看看RS-25的情况
Aerojet received $570 million just to revamp the RS-25D's to be recertified for flight.
洛克达因获得了5.7亿美元的资金 只是为了改造RS-25D 使其重新获得飞行认证
I mean, yes, there was a lot of work that went into this.
我是指 是的 这里面有很多工作要做
www.nasa.gov/exploration/systems/sls/fs/rs25_core_stage_engines.html
I mean, testing dozens of engines and recertifying them for new profiles,
也就是 测试了十几台(16)发动机 并对它们进行了新的认证
but again, the hardware already existed
但同样 这些设备已经存在
and to spend over half a billion dollars to get some engines ready to fly
并花费5亿多美元让一些发动机准备好飞行
that have already flown on the Space Shuttle is just kind of hard to swallow.
甚至是已经在航天飞机上飞行过的(14台飞行过 2台未飞过) 实在是有点难以接受
And NASA has officially paid for 24 more RS-25s for a total of $3.5 billion,
而NASA已经正式支付了另外24台RS-25的费用 共计35亿美元
which includes $1 billion to restart production.
其中包括10亿美元用于重启生产
After the restart and the initial 6 engines, $1.8 billion was spent for just 18 engines.
在重启生产最初的6台发动机之后 仅仅18台发动机就花了18亿美元
粗体是提醒不要断章取义
So the cost per engine after all of that stuff is about a hundred million dollars.
所以 这么算下来 每台发动机的成本大约是1亿美元
Yep.
没错
That's about as expensive as a reusable Falcon Heavy for just one engine.
这么一台发动机的造价 和可重复使用的重型猎鹰的成本差不多
Or there's the Interim Cryogenic Upper Stage
或者是过渡型低温上面级
that will cost right around half a billion dollars for three units and one test unit.
三台设备和一台测试设备的成本将达到5亿美元左右
So we're looking at an upper stage that will cost about $125 million just for the upper stage.
那么 这样一个上面级要花费差不多1.25亿美元 还只是上面级
Or what about the mobile launch tower?
或者移动发射塔呢？
I didn't even want to get started on the mobile launch tower.
移动发射塔我都不想提了
This one tower has wound up costing about $1 billion.
这一座塔的成本已经达到了10亿美元左右
Yup. This steel constructed tower with some, uh, umbilicals hold downs and the crew access arm
是的 这座钢结构的塔楼有一些 呃 脐带固定器和乘员通道臂
has somehow ended up costing over half as much as the world's tallest building, the Burj Khalifa.
不知何故 最终成本超过了世界最高建筑哈利法塔的一半
How, how does that happen?
为什么会这样呢？
You could literally stack the nearly $1 billion that it took to build the mobile launch tower
你可以把这造发射塔的近10亿美元叠起来
and it would literally reach space.
都可以达到太空那么高了
But lastly, maybe the most damning thing
但最后 也许最令人震惊的事情
has been the amount of money Boeing has received to build the core stage.
是波音得到的用于建造芯级的资金额度
Boeing has received about $6.7 billion to design build and test just two core stages.
仅设计建造和测试两枚芯级 波音就获得了约67亿美元
How is that possible? This is what I don't get. And I'm sorry.
这怎么可能呢？这是我不明白的地方 我很抱歉
It just doesn't make any sense to me. Yes, they are using a new material.
我想不通啊 是的 他们使用的是一种新材料
Yes. They set up the world's largest friction stir welder and had some problems with it.
是的 他们安装了世界上最大的摩擦搅拌焊机 但出现了一些问题
Yes. A tornado ripped through Michoud. Yes, they dropped a tank once. Whoops.
是的 一场龙卷风席卷了密歇根州米乔德(装配厂) 是的 芜湖 有个储罐摔坏了
But still that's just ridiculous.
但这也太荒唐了吧
Why was there not a much more firm price cap on all this
为什么在这里面没有一个更坚定的价格上限呢？
that put a little fire under Boeing's butt to get this all done on time and at a better price.
给波音的屁股底下烧点儿火 让他们以更好的价格按时完成这一切
Frankly, NASA is going to have to make up for SLS as costs
坦率地说 (在这种不断要钱的情况下) NASA是得给SLS加钱
because at best as less costs are irresponsible and frustrating.
因为即使在最好的情况下 减少成本只是不负责任和令人沮丧的
At worse, it's a blatant misuse of taxpayer money
更糟的情况下 (如减少成本后出了事故) 简直就是公然滥用纳税人的钱
and feels borderline criminal.
感觉就像在违法的边缘反复横跳
It took until 2019 before NASA's newest administrator.
直到2019年 NASA最新的局长
Jim Bridenstine really came in and finally whipped things into shape.
Jim Bridenstine才上任 并最终将事情打理得井井有条
Jim started threatening to use commercial rockets to get us to the moon by 2024.
Jim开始威胁要在2024年之前用商业火箭登月
And Boeing seemed to get the memo
而波音似乎闻风而动
because all of a sudden we saw them finally get into gear.
因为突然间我们看到他们终于进入了状态
But should he have just followed through with that threat?
但是 他是否应该就这样贯彻这一威胁呢？
What options are there really in the commercial world that can do the job of SLS and Orion?
在商业世界里 有什么选项能真正做到SLS和猎户座的工作？
Well, we'll save that for part three,
好吧 就这一话题 我们将保留到第三部分
when we look at what could actually do the same amount of work
也就是当我们审视过有啥东西可以实际完成同样的工作量
and safely replace SLS for getting humans to and from the moon,
并安全地取代SLS 能载人往返月球时
we'll go over all the commercial options, including Starship and Falcon Heavy,
我们将介绍所有的商业选择 包括Starship和重型猎鹰
since you guys ask me about this all the time,
既然你们经常问我这个问题
and we actually look at the feasibility and the costs associated with those.
而且我们实际上(已经)研究过(这些项目的)可行性与相关的成本
But now just a reminder for all of us, me included,
但现在只是提醒下大家 包括我在内
if your blood is boiling, like mine is right now,
如果你的血液已经沸腾了 就像我现在一样
and if you need an understanding of why there's that cost plus contract,
如果你需要了解为什么会有成本加合同
b23.tv/av285667766
remember to go rewatch the last video about SLS and Starship
记得去重看上一个关于SLS和Starship的视频
to help put all of that into perspective.
这样就能搞清楚
But in reality, it is a necessary evil to ensure that this stuff actually happens.
但实际上 为了保证卫星落地 这是必要之恶
But now speaking of commercial options,
但既然说到商业选项
let's talk about the good parts of the Artemis program.
让我们来谈谈阿尔忒弥斯计划里好的部分
阿尔忒弥斯中好的部分
So now onto the good parts of the Artemis program.
那么现在说说阿尔忒弥斯计划中好的部分吧
No, no, actually I take that back for all the negativity and cost overruns we're seeing with SLS.
不 不 实际上我要收回这句表示SLS负面新闻和成本超支的话
I actually honestly am really glad that we're going to have that capability.
老实说 我真的很高兴我们能拥有这种能力
I don't want it canceled before we have another readily available vehicle.
我不希望在可替代的方案出现之前把它取消
So although insanely insanely frustrating and expensive SLS is a good thing right now.
所以 虽然SLS的价格很贵 也很令人沮丧 但它现在是一件好事
Okay. So let's try that again.
好吧 那我们再试一次
Onto the better part of the Artemis program, the Human Landing System,
到了阿尔忒弥斯计划中更好的部分 载人登月系统
which will utilize the fixed price contracting scheme that we talked about in that last video,
这将利用我们在上一个视频中谈到的固定价格合同的方案
but it's awesome to see NASA utilizing it on a more ambitious scale.
但看到NASA在更大规模的地方使用它 是很好的
After all NASA didn't really give any direction on how these companies were to build their Landers.
毕竟NASA并没有真的告诉这些公司到底如何建造他们的登月舱
They didn't say how big or small to make them.
他们没说(尺寸上)要造多大多小
They didn't which rockets they had to take them to the moon,
他们没说要用哪种火箭(把登月舱)发射到月球
but they just really let the companies innovate and submit proposals.
但他们真的只是让这些公司提交创新的方案
So again, this is much more akin to the Commercial Crew Program.
那么再提一下 这就更像是商业载人计划了
NASA had a set of requirements and accepted proposals.
NASA有一套要求 并接受提案
Through this commercial partnership, it'll allow for multiple partners to innovate and deliver.
通过这种商业合作 会有多个合作伙伴进行创新和交付
So we can always have some non commonality and redundancy in providers.
所以 我们总可以在供应商方面有一些独特性和冗余性
Redundancy is after all a very good thing.
冗余毕竟是一件非常好的事情
Just like with the Commercial Crew Program, how we have Boeing and SpaceX,
就像商业载人计划 波音和SpaceX
which have completely different parts and different providers,
有着完全不同的部件和不同的供应商
no commonality really between those two systems at all.
这两个系统之间没有任何共性
And that's a good thing because as we know,
而这是一件好事 因为我们知道
Boeing's had some problems and they're really behind schedule
波音出了些问题 而且他们真的落后于计划
while SpaceX is able to continue fulfilling NASA's missions.
而SpaceX能继续完成NASA的任务
But of course there's still some unknowns because we don't know the exact numbers here on
但当然 还是有一些未知数 因为我们不知道具体的数字
how much the human landing system will cost.
也就是载人登月系统的成本是多少
So we can't really project if it's going to make up for the cost of SLS yet.
所以我们还不能真的推算它(的低成本) 是否能弥补SLS的(高)成本 (从而拉低平均成本)
But my gut feeling is if Artemis truly becomes a sustained and continually funded project,
但我的直觉是 如果阿尔忒弥斯真的成为一个持续不断的资助项目
and if the Landers end up being reused,
而如果登月舱最终被重复使用
they could be a huge win for NASA.
这对NASA而言可能是一个很大的胜利
I mean, even the least reusable vehicle, Blue Origins' National Team Lander,
我是指 即使是最不能重复使用的航天器 蓝色起源的国家队登月器
only ditches the descent stage and reuses both the orbital tug stage and the ascent stage,
也只是抛弃了下降级 而重复使用轨道转移级和上升级
which means there's potential to save a lot of money
这意味着有可能会节省很多钱
when you don't throw away 100% of your billion dollar Lunar Lander with each and every mission.
当你不把你那价值十亿美元的登月器在每次任务中都扔掉的时候
And then you have Starship,
然后你就有了Starship
which if fully reusable and launched on a fully reusable rocket,
如果可以完全重复使用 并且用完全重复使用的火箭发射
which of course is the plan,
这当然是计划中的
it could end up being a huge cost savings with the potential to truly change the game.
它最终可能会节约大量成本 并有可能真正改变游戏规则
So unlike Apollo, which had very little chance of becoming cheaper as time went on,
所以不像阿波罗 随着时间的推移 变得便宜的可能性很小
the Artemis program is built around the evolving technologies,
而阿尔忒弥斯计划是围绕着不断发展的技术而建立的
reuse and eventual cost savings.
重复使用 并最终节省成本
So the longer the program lasts, the cheaper and more sustainable, it should actually get.
因此 该计划持续的时间越长 实际上就应该越便宜且越可持续
It's baked into the program, which is awesome.
很妙的是 这一要求是深深烙印在该计划中的
总结
So, Artemis versus Apollo.
那么 阿尔忒弥斯与阿波罗的比较
Honestly, a part of me just really wishes that NASA had rebuilt the Saturn V
老实说 我内心有一部分真的希望NASA重建土星五号
found ways to make it cheaper than before, and just done things the old way,
并找到了比以前更便宜的方法来实现这种老方案
because it seems really hard to justify SLS.
因为这似乎真的很难证明SLS的合理性
If reusing the literal leftover hardware that's sitting on shelves
如果真的是重复使用现有的剩余设备
was meant to make the rocket more cost effective.
是为了让火箭成本更低
It sure didn't help.
(对于SLS和猎户座而言) 这肯定没起作用
And then once they had to open up new and old lines of manufacturing,
然后 一旦到了他们得开辟新的以及旧的制造线的时候
why not just build F-1's and the whole Saturn V with slightly updated and modern technology.
为什么不直接制造F-1和整个土星五号 并带有一点儿更新和更现代的技术呢
It's also a shame that Orion has such a small and relatively incapable service module
另外让人感到遗憾的是 猎户座的服务舱如此之小 能力相对也要差不少
since SLS can't even take anything bigger the moon for now.
因为目前SLS发射到月球的运力本来不大 (所以猎户座服务舱能力不足就更加拉垮)
Of course, if it gets upgraded, it could eventually do more,
当然 如果SLS得到升级 那么还是有能力做更多的事情
对于阿尔忒弥斯计划的任务(功能)而言是弱于土星五号，但如果以Block 1B的43t TLI能力而言，
已经可以打阿波罗飞船基础版(44t)了，比阿波罗15号之前的土星五号TLI能力(41t)略高，
来源：en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Saturn_V#Technology
but still, it's still less even with the Block 1B than the Saturn V.
但还是要比土星五号鶸 即使是Block 1B
But it just feels like this is the 21st century,
但就是觉得这是21世纪了
the rockets should by no measure be going backwards.
火箭在任何情况下(性能)都不应该开倒车
They shouldn't be less capable and more expensive.
它们不应该是能力更弱但更昂贵
We should be getting cheaper and more capable rockets.
我们应该得到更便宜 更强的火箭
And I know it doesn't really feel like it,
我知道这并不是说真的感觉就是这样
but by the time you actually factor in all of the development costs and the different development rockets,
但当你实际考虑到不同火箭的开发成本时候
SLS is actually cheaper than the Saturn V.
SLS其实比土星五号更便宜
Especially if you only consider the Saturn V's that flew and subtract the development costs,
尤其是如果你只考虑土星五号的发射成本 不考虑开发成本
the SLS will be substantially cheaper, almost any way you cut it.
SLS的价格会便宜更多 不管你怎么算
But as far as the Artemis program as a whole is concerned,
但就整个阿尔忒弥斯计划而言
NASA is strongly leaning into the commercial sector.
NASA正大力向商业领域靠拢
And I think that's going to be a huge win.
我认为这会走向一个巨大的胜利
And although NASA has already ordered up way more SLS's than I think any of us would prefer,
虽然NASA已经订购了更多的SLS 多到也许我们中的任何一个人都会觉得太多了
it at least ensures we won't have a gap in provider coverage like the nine year gap the US had
在供应商覆盖的产品范围层面 它至少可以确保不会断档 不会像之前美国的那9年
when the Shuttle Program ended before the Commercial Crew Program was ready to fly.
也就是在商业载人计划准备发射之前就砍掉了航天飞机计划
And this is vital.
而这是至关重要的
It's too easy for NASA to get the carpet pulled out from underneath them
对于NASA而言 太容易被致命打击
with each and every administration change.
也就是在每届政府更换的时候
So by committing to something, even if it's expensive, it at least gets the ball rolling.
所以 通过承诺一些事情 哪怕是昂贵的 至少可以起步
But when comparing Apollo to the Artemis program a lot has changed,
但是 当把阿波罗计划和阿尔忒弥斯计划进行比较时 很多事情都发生了变化
but perhaps the biggest change is the risks themselves.
但也许最大的变化是风险本身
Because the risks have shifted.
因为风险已经转移了
The Apollo program's biggest risks were with human lives.
阿波罗计划最大的风险是人的生命
Whereas the Artemis program's biggest risk is more of a funding risk
而阿尔忒弥斯计划最大的风险则是资金
and the constant fear of cancellation.
和不断面临取消的恐惧
And maybe that just isn't as sexy.
也许就是因为阿尔忒弥斯的吸引力不够
After all NASA had what feels like unlimited funding to get the Apollo program sprinting ahead of the Soviet Union.
毕竟想当年NASA可是有着几乎无限的资金来完成阿波罗计划 (就为了)冲刺在苏联前面
And now NASA has to play far more politics to ensure a program's survival.
而现在NASA就得玩更多的政治来确保一个项目的生存
I think my generation and future generations
我想我们这一代和未来的人们
just craves the excitement, the pace and the innovation of the Apollo era.
只是渴望阿波罗时代刺激的创新节奏
And we just ended up scratching our heads at why everything is taking so long
但是最后只能挠头想想为什么所有事都要花这么长的时间？
for what feels like bad sequel to the first movie.
就像是一部电影的辣鸡续集
After all, there is no way you can deny
毕竟 你没法否认
that the Apollo program isn't easily, one of humanity's greatest achievements to date.
阿波罗计划是人类迄今为止最伟大的成就之一
It might forever be one of the biggest bookmark moments in the history books.
它可能永远是史书上最值得纪念的时刻之一
I mean, it's absolutely incredible that humans figured all this stuff out at a time
我是指 这是绝对不可思议的 人类竟然在一段时期(一个年代)里搞懂了所有这些东西
when computers here's where the size of a room and most calculations done by a slide rule.
那时 电脑的大小和一个房间一样大 而大多数计算都由计算尺完成
So to even compare the two programs side by side is maybe a bit unfair,
那么 即使将这两个程序并列比较 或许也有点不公平
but since we haven't seen humans on the moon in 50 years,
但由于我们已经50年没有载人登月过了
it is important to weigh in all the facts to see if we're actually going to do it this time,
重要的是要权衡所有的事实 来看看这次能否实现
or if we're just going to get our hopes up and we're going watch another program get canceled
或者 我们刚有了期待却落空了 不过是另一个计划被砍
and see another decade slip between our fingers.
并眼睁睁看着另一个十年从我们的指缝间溜走
It's just a weird convergence in history
这只是一个奇怪的历史交汇点
that by the time we have a program up and running that can actually return humans to the moon,
等到真正能让人类返回月球的计划开始运行的时候
it just so happens that the commercial industry is booming
也正是商业(航天)领域蓬勃发展的时候
and it has matured to the point of being able to do so much of the work.
并且商业产品已经成熟到能够完成这么多的工作
And it starts to make the program that's been in the works for almost a decade,
而这些开始让这个已经酝酿了近十年的阿尔忒弥斯计划
suddenly look 45 years old.
突然看起来老了45岁
But the good news is that just by having these vehicles paid for,
但好消息是 只要花钱买了这些航天器
it helps ensure the success of the many commercial partners involved
它就有助于确保许多商业伙伴的成功
and other future commercial partners.
以及其他未来的商业伙伴
So to me, Artemis, isn't Apollo 2.0.
所以在我看来 阿尔忒弥斯 并不是阿波罗2.0
Artemis is more like the first commercial flights across the Atlantic on the FW 200 condor
阿尔忒弥斯更像是FW200兀鹰式客机首次跨越大西洋的商业飞行
compared to Charles Lindbergh's daring and dangerous flight on his single engine Spirit of St. Louis.
与查尔斯林德伯格在单发飞机圣路易斯精神号上进行的大胆而危险的飞行相比
Artemis is setting itself up to be sustainable in a different way.
阿尔忒弥斯正在以一种不同的方式设置项目的可持续性
Hopefully aligning the program to survive multiple administrations
希望通过计划的调整 使之能在多届政府中生存下来
while paving the way for cheaper and more competitive commercial options.
同时为更便宜 更具竞争力的商业选项铺平道路
And that's definitely something to be excited about.
而这绝对是值得兴奋的事情
So what are your thoughts?
那么你有什么想法呢？
Do you think the Artemis program is a step in the right direction
or do you feel like NASA is moving backwards and should have just completely redone the Apollo program?
Do you think this wacky structure will end up making Artemis successful long run
or do you think it'll cancel before any humans make it to the moon?
Let me know your thoughts in the comments below.
Did you guys those awesome 3D renders that were used in the video?
Those were from Casper Stanley. You definitely have to find him on Twitter.
He has some awesome work. He's constantly making really,
really impressive things.
So be sure and give him a follow on Twitter
and also check out his awesome rocket Explorer App as well. Of course,
I owe a huge thank you to my Patreon supporters for helping make this
and all other everyday astronaut content possible.
If you want to help me script and research and get your thoughts on videos
and see little sneak peeks and see the scripts and stuff before I shoot,
consider becoming a Patreon supporter where you'll gain access to our exclusive subreddit,
our exclusive discord channel and exclusive monthly live streams by heading over to patreon.
com/everydayastronaut. And while you're online,
be sure and check out my web store for awesome shirts like this lunar mission shirt,
which is really cool. And on the back,
it even has the Apollo Lunar Lander,
but we have lots of other really cool merchandise,
including brand new Full Flow Staged Combustion Cycle hoodies,
future Martian T-shirts new key chains, lots of awesome stuff.
So just shop around.
I promise you'll find some really cool stuff at everydayastronaut.com/shop.
Thanks everybody that's going to do it for me.
谢谢大家观看 本期节目到这里就结束了
I'm Tim Dodd, the Everyday Astronaut.
我是Tim Dodd 每日宇航员
将太空的知识带给地球上的普通人